<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Liza Katz's Blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Latest blog posts about AI, search technologies, and software engineering]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 07:22:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Leading an AI Hackathon at Hopper Security]]></title><description><![CDATA[Led an AI hackathon at Hopper Security, exploring advanced LLM architectures and helping teams tackle real GenAI product challenges.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/hopper-security-ai-hackathon/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/hopper-security-ai-hackathon/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Had an incredible day leading an &lt;strong&gt;AI Hackathon&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hopper.security/&quot;&gt;Hopper Security&lt;/a&gt;! Watching teams tackle GenAI challenges and design creative solutions for their product was energizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started with LLM-powered application patterns that go beyond basic prompting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced RAG Techniques&lt;/strong&gt; - Moving past simple retrieval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agents and Agentic AI&lt;/strong&gt; - Building autonomous, reasoning systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Playbook-driven agents&lt;/strong&gt; - Structured workflows with LLM flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code analysis with AST and Embeddings&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding codebases semantically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These architectural patterns gave teams a foundation to think bigger about what’s possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the real highlight was sitting with each team to plan their approach. We worked through problem framing, architecture selection, and feasibility—ensuring ideas were both ambitious and achievable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each team brought unique perspectives. The discussions went deep, challenging assumptions and exploring trade-offs between different technical approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to see these ideas evolve into real product features that push the boundaries of what’s possible with GenAI in security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Looking to energize your team with a GenAI hackathon or workshop? I help organizations explore cutting-edge AI techniques and build practical solutions. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/lizak/&quot;&gt;Let’s connect on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; to discuss how we can bring innovation to your team!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Advanced RAG Workshop at Astrix Security]]></title><description><![CDATA[Delivered a hands-on workshop on advanced LLM applications and RAG techniques at Astrix Security, covering embeddings, retrieval strategies, and practical experimentation.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/astrix-security-advanced-rag-workshop/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/astrix-security-advanced-rag-workshop/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This workshop was delivered as part of my work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/&quot;&gt;Big Data Boutique&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a fantastic time delivering an &lt;strong&gt;Advanced RAG Workshop&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrix.security/&quot;&gt;Astrix Security&lt;/a&gt;! This was a deep dive into building production-grade LLM applications with a focus on Retrieval-Augmented Generation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What We Covered&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop combined theory with hands-on experimentation, focusing on practical techniques teams can implement immediately:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding embedding models and their trade-offs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semantic vs. keyword search: when to use what&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vector database options and considerations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chunking strategies beyond naive splitting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hybrid search combining multiple retrieval methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experimenting with AWS Knowledgebase on real datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thank You!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to the Astrix Security team for hosting such an engaged and curious group!
Looking forward to seeing what the team builds with these techniques!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/v2/D4E22AQGD1RuEz7FzUA/feedshare-shrink_2048_1536/B4EZrWRFNqIoA0-/0/1764531394735?e=1767830400&amp;#x26;v=beta&amp;#x26;t=A9DHQGDVnMBi4yI7rhCA6pAqaYwMvYd-aEKI0XLViuI&quot; alt=&quot;Workshop at Astrix&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interested in hosting a similar workshop for your team? I offer customized RAG and GenAI workshops tailored to your specific use cases and technology stack. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/lizak/&quot;&gt;Reach out via LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; to discuss!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Certification: AWS Certified Data Engineer – Associate]]></title><description><![CDATA[Achieved AWS Certified Data Engineer – Associate certification, validating expertise in data ingestion, transformation, orchestration, and data lifecycle management on AWS.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-data-engineer-associate-certification/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-data-engineer-associate-certification/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to share that I have earned the &lt;strong&gt;AWS Certified Data Engineer – Associate&lt;/strong&gt; certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AWS Certified Data Engineer – Associate validates skills and knowledge in core data-related AWS services, including the ability to ingest and transform data, orchestrate data pipelines while applying programming concepts, design data models, manage data lifecycles, and ensure data quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can learn more about this certification on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/certification/certified-data-engineer-associate/&quot;&gt;official AWS page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Speaking at Build Stuff Vilnius 2025]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'll be speaking at Build Stuff in Vilnius, Lithuania on the 3rd of December 2025. Looking forward to it!]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/buildstuff-vilnius-2025/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/buildstuff-vilnius-2025/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ll be speaking at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildstuff.events/&quot;&gt;Build Stuff&lt;/a&gt; in Vilnius, Lithuania this December. Looking forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building Advanced RAGs with Elasticsearch / OpenSearch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAG (Retrieval Augmented Generation) is built in three steps: understanding the query, executing a retrieval step, and generating a response. Each step has its own unique characteristics and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this session, we’ll go through common pitfalls (and solutions!) for each step, and demonstrate how you can build an efficient RAG using Elasticsearch or OpenSearch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What to expect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll cover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Query processing and intent understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective retrieval strategies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Response generation techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-world examples and practical patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus is on the practical stuff - the challenges you actually run into when building RAG systems in production, not just the happy path demos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When:&lt;/strong&gt; December 3-5, 2025&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Where:&lt;/strong&gt; Vilnius, Lithuania&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Conference:&lt;/strong&gt; Built Stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in attending, there’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildstuff.events/9800492&quot;&gt;15% discount available&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[AWS RAG & GenAI Innovation Workshop 2025]]></title><description><![CDATA[Delivering a hands-on RAG workshop with the AWS team to help customers build a real demo on their own data.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-rag-genai-innovation-workshop-2025/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-rag-genai-innovation-workshop-2025/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As part of my work with BigData Boutique, I’ll be teaming up with the AWS team to deliver the &lt;strong&gt;AWS RAG &amp;#x26; GenAI Innovation Workshop 2025&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a focused, practical session where we help a customer build a working Retrieval-Augmented Generation demo on &lt;em&gt;their own&lt;/em&gt; data—not sample docs. The goal: leave with something tangible you can iterate on internally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we actually do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the user problem and pick a target use case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collect and lightly structure a slice of your real content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chunk + preprocess (keep it simple, explain trade-offs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate embeddings and load a vector store&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wire retrieval + LLM prompt flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add basic guardrails &amp;#x26; relevance sanity checks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick evaluation loop (spot checks + simple metrics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave you with next-step pointers (hardening, scaling, monitoring)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who it’s for&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams who want to move from slides / pilots to something concrete, fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Link&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshop page: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/workshop/aws-rag-genai-innovation-workshop-2025&quot;&gt;https://bigdataboutique.com/workshop/aws-rag-genai-innovation-workshop-2025&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to explore running a similar session on your data, feel free to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Certification: AWS Certified Machine Learning Engineer – Associate]]></title><description><![CDATA[Achieved AWS Certified Machine Learning Engineer – Associate certification, validating expertise in designing, implementing, and maintaining ML solutions on AWS.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-ai-associate-certification/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-ai-associate-certification/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share that I’ve earned the &lt;strong&gt;AWS Certified Machine Learning Engineer – Associate&lt;/strong&gt; certification!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AWS Certified Machine Learning Engineer – Associate validates expertise in designing, implementing, deploying, and maintaining machine learning solutions on AWS. This certification demonstrates proficiency in ML engineering practices, including data preparation, model development, deployment automation, and monitoring ML systems in production environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can learn more about this certification on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/certification/certified-machine-learning-engineer-associate/&quot;&gt;official AWS page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Speaking at PyCon Israel 2025: WTF Are Embeddings? A Software Engineer's Take]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm excited to announce that I'll be speaking at PyCon Israel 2025 with a talk that demystifies embeddings for software engineers - no ML PhD required!]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/pycon-2025-embeddings-talk/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/pycon-2025-embeddings-talk/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DJPBdpzQnDs&quot;&gt;PyCon WTF Are Embeddings recording&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m thrilled to announce that I’ll be speaking at &lt;a href=&quot;https://python.org.il/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyCon Israel 2025&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; this September! My talk, titled &lt;strong&gt;“WTF Are Embeddings? A software engineer’s take”&lt;/strong&gt;, is scheduled for September 9th at 15:30 in Hall 7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Talk: WTF Are Embeddings?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embeddings are everywhere in modern AI - powering search engines, recommendation systems, and those surprisingly accurate chatbots we interact with daily. But for many software engineers, they remain a mysterious black box wrapped in academic jargon and complex mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s exactly what my talk aims to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What You’ll Learn&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“WTF Are Embeddings?”&lt;/strong&gt; is designed specifically for developers who want to understand embeddings without needing a data science PhD. Here’s what we’ll cover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What embeddings actually are&lt;/strong&gt; - in plain English, not mathematical formulas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-world examples&lt;/strong&gt; showing how words, products, and even bananas become vectors in high-dimensional space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical Python implementations&lt;/strong&gt; using everyday tools you already know&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When and why to use embeddings&lt;/strong&gt; in your own projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Common pitfalls and how to avoid them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See You There!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re attending PyCon Israel 2025, please come to Hall 7 on September 9th at 15:30. Bring your questions, your curiosity, and your willingness to finally understand what all the embedding fuss is about!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can’t make it to the conference? Don’t worry - I’ll be sharing key insights and examples from the talk right here on my blog after the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conference Details:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event&lt;/strong&gt;: PyCon Israel 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk&lt;/strong&gt;: “WTF Are Embeddings? A software engineer’s take”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: September 9, 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 15:30-15:50 (Asia/Jerusalem)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Hall 7&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language&lt;/strong&gt;: English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to meeting fellow Python enthusiasts and sharing the fascinating world of embeddings with you all!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Upcoming Webinar: RAG with OpenSearch - A Crash Course for Building RAG Applications]]></title><description><![CDATA[Join me on July 30th for a comprehensive workshop on building production-ready RAG applications with OpenSearch, covering everything from data preparation to LLM integration.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/rag-opensearch-webinar-announcement/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/rag-opensearch-webinar-announcement/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce that I’ll be delivering a comprehensive workshop on &lt;strong&gt;July 30th, 2025&lt;/strong&gt; titled ”&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/events/7350900293720584194/&quot;&gt;RAG with OpenSearch: A Crash Course for Building RAG Applications&lt;/a&gt;” hosted by Big Data Boutique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What You’ll Learn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This hands-on workshop is designed to take you from concept to implementation, covering the complete RAG pipeline with OpenSearch. Whether you’re working on proof-of-concept projects or looking to build production-ready solutions, this session will provide practical insights you can apply immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Complete RAG Pipeline Coverage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll walk through every step of building a robust RAG system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🔧 Data Preparation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structuring documents for optimal chunking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metadata enrichment strategies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient indexing approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🧠 Embeddings &amp;#x26; Vector Storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choosing the right embedding model for your use case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generating semantic vectors at scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing and retrieving vectors efficiently in OpenSearch with k-NN and HNSW&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🔍 Hybrid Search Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blending keyword-based and semantic retrieval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimizing for better relevance and accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-world search scenarios and solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🤖 LLM Integration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passing context effectively to language models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre- and post-processing techniques for better responses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generating accurate, grounded answers with LLMs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who Should Attend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop is &lt;strong&gt;ideal for&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers&lt;/strong&gt; building AI-powered applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Engineers&lt;/strong&gt; working with search and retrieval systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Practitioners&lt;/strong&gt; looking to move from proof-of-concept to production-ready solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone interested in understanding how modern RAG systems work under the hood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having worked extensively with both Elasticsearch and OpenSearch, and now leading GenAI initiatives at Big Data Boutique, I’ve seen firsthand the challenges teams face when building RAG applications. This workshop addresses the gap between tutorial-level examples and production-ready systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll learn not just &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to build RAG applications, but &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; certain design decisions matter, and how to avoid common pitfalls that can derail projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building on Real Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop draws from my experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a former Elastic team member who worked on search infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leading GenAI projects at Big Data Boutique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/opensearch-vector-database-tutorial/&quot;&gt;OpenSearch vector search tutorials&lt;/a&gt; that were &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/opensearch-blog-feature/&quot;&gt;featured on the official OpenSearch blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building production RAG systems for various clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What You’ll Take Away&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of this session, you’ll have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear understanding&lt;/strong&gt; of the complete RAG pipeline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; for setting up and optimizing RAG systems with OpenSearch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Production insights&lt;/strong&gt; for building scalable, reliable solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best practices&lt;/strong&gt; for data ingestion, indexing, and retrieval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-world examples&lt;/strong&gt; you can adapt to your own projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Join the Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📅 &lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: July 30th, 2025&lt;br&gt;
🌐 &lt;strong&gt;Format&lt;/strong&gt;: Online event&lt;br&gt;
🏢 &lt;strong&gt;Host&lt;/strong&gt;: Big Data Boutique&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/events/7350900293720584194/&quot;&gt;Register on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to secure your spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re just starting with RAG applications or looking to optimize existing systems, this workshop will provide valuable insights to help you build better, more effective retrieval-augmented generation solutions with OpenSearch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to sharing practical knowledge and answering your questions about building production-ready RAG systems. See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Workshop: Introduction to RAG in Production]]></title><description><![CDATA[Learn to build and deploy production-ready Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems with hands-on guidance from preprocessing to evaluation.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/rag-production-workshop/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/rag-production-workshop/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce my new workshop: &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to RAG in Production&lt;/strong&gt; - a comprehensive hands-on session designed for teams looking to implement robust RAG systems in real-world environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What You’ll Learn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Foundation &amp;#x26; Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to GenAI and LLMs&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding the landscape and capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LLM Application Architectures&lt;/strong&gt; - Design patterns for scalable systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embeddings Overview&lt;/strong&gt; - What are embeddings and how they power semantic search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector Database Comparison&lt;/strong&gt; - Choosing the right storage solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Exploration Fundamentals&lt;/strong&gt; - Analyzing and understanding your data for RAG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Production RAG Pipeline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll build a complete RAG system covering every critical step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Document Preprocessing&lt;/strong&gt; - Text extraction, chunking strategies, and optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Ingestion&lt;/strong&gt; - Efficient embedding generation and storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Querying &amp;#x26; Search&lt;/strong&gt; - Semantic retrieval and relevance scoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Document Post-processing&lt;/strong&gt; - Context ranking and filtering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer Generation&lt;/strong&gt; - Prompt engineering and response optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt; - Metrics, testing frameworks, and quality assurance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Production Challenges&lt;/strong&gt; - Scaling, monitoring, and maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who Should Attend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop is ideal for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineering teams implementing RAG systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data scientists exploring production deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product managers overseeing AI initiatives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CTOs evaluating RAG solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Format&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive 3-hour workshop combining theory with practical implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in bringing this workshop to your team?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:your-email&quot;&gt;Contact me&lt;/a&gt; to discuss custom sessions tailored to your specific use cases and tech stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Available for both in-person and remote delivery.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Recognized as a Top Voice in Search Tech by Pulse Support]]></title><description><![CDATA[I was honored to be featured in Pulse Support's 'Top Voices in Search Tech' initiative, sharing insights about my journey in search technologies and GenAI.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/top-voice-search-recognition/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/top-voice-search-recognition/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m honored to share that I’ve been recognized as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pulse.support/top-voices/liza-katz&quot;&gt;Top Voice in Search Tech&lt;/a&gt; by Pulse Support as part of their carefully curated showcase of influential search technology professionals from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Recognition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulse Support’s “Top Voices in Search-Tech” initiative highlights impactful professionals who are shaping the search technology landscape. Being included in this showcase alongside other industry leaders is both humbling and exciting - it reflects the work I’ve been doing over the past 20+ years in search, observability, and now GenAI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Full Interview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the complete interview and learn more about my perspectives on search technology: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pulse.support/top-voices/liza-katz&quot;&gt;Top Voices in Search Tech: Liza Katz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to Pulse Support for this recognition and the opportunity to share insights with the broader search community. Here’s to continued innovation in making information more discoverable and actionable for everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Featured on the Official OpenSearch Blog: Recipes to Vectors Tutorial]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm thrilled to share that my vector search tutorial was featured on the official OpenSearch blog - a significant recognition from the OpenSearch community.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/opensearch-blog-feature/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/opensearch-blog-feature/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m absolutely thrilled to share that my tutorial on building hybrid search applications has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensearch.org/blog/recipes-to-vectors-building-a-hybrid-search-app-with-opensearch/&quot;&gt;featured on the official OpenSearch blog&lt;/a&gt;! This is an incredible honor and recognition from the OpenSearch community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Major Milestone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being featured on the official OpenSearch blog represents a significant milestone in my journey as a search technology expert. The OpenSearch project is used by thousands of organizations worldwide, and having my work showcased on their platform validates the practical value of the tutorial and my approach to vector search implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Feature Covers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog post, titled &lt;strong&gt;“Recipes to vectors: Building a hybrid search app with OpenSearch”&lt;/strong&gt;, presents the complete tutorial I originally developed for Big Data Boutique. The OpenSearch team recognized the educational value and practical applicability of the content, making it available to their broader developer community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tutorial demonstrates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complete end-to-end implementation&lt;/strong&gt; using real recipe data from Kaggle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical embedding construction&lt;/strong&gt; combining multiple fields for optimal semantic representation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Index configuration&lt;/strong&gt; with proper k-NN settings and vector field mappings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hands-on code examples&lt;/strong&gt; available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BigDataBoutique/opensearch-semantic-search-tutorial&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three search approaches&lt;/strong&gt;: keyword search, semantic search, and hybrid search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Power of Real-World Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this tutorial particularly valuable is its use of actual recipe data - showing both structured fields (categories, cooking time) and unstructured content (ingredients, instructions). This demonstrates when to use traditional keyword search versus semantic search, and how to combine them effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tutorial includes practical examples like finding “Asian-inspired chicken recipes with noodles and peanuts” through semantic search, then filtering for specific categories using hybrid approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Community Recognition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the OpenSearch team feature my work is especially meaningful given my background. As a former Elastic team member who now works extensively with both Elasticsearch and OpenSearch, I understand the importance of providing clear, practical guidance for developers building vector-powered applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feature includes a dedicated author profile highlighting my work in search infrastructure, generative AI, and open source - positioning me as a trusted voice in the OpenSearch community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building on Previous Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This recognition builds on the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/vector-search-introduction/&quot;&gt;foundational vector search concepts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/semantic-search-elasticsearch-tutorial/&quot;&gt;Elasticsearch implementations&lt;/a&gt; I’ve shared previously. It demonstrates how the same principles apply across different search platforms while highlighting OpenSearch-specific implementation details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What This Means&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being featured on the official OpenSearch blog means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community validation&lt;/strong&gt; of my technical expertise and teaching approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broader reach&lt;/strong&gt; for practical vector search education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recognition&lt;/strong&gt; as a contributor to the OpenSearch ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Platform&lt;/strong&gt; for sharing best practices with thousands of developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Featured Tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the complete tutorial on the official OpenSearch blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensearch.org/blog/recipes-to-vectors-building-a-hybrid-search-app-with-opensearch/&quot;&gt;Recipes to vectors: Building a hybrid search app with OpenSearch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to the OpenSearch team for this recognition and excited to continue contributing to the community’s understanding of vector search and hybrid retrieval systems. This feature reinforces my commitment to making advanced search technologies accessible and practical for developers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Presented at the First OpenSearch Tel Aviv Meetup: WTF Are Embeddings?]]></title><description><![CDATA[I had the pleasure of presenting at the inaugural OpenSearch Tel Aviv meetup, sharing insights about embeddings in a fun and educational talk.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/opensearch-tel-aviv-meetup/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/opensearch-tel-aviv-meetup/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of presenting at the very first &lt;strong&gt;OpenSearch Tel Aviv meetup&lt;/strong&gt; hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/&quot;&gt;Big Data Boutique&lt;/a&gt; this past Monday! The event, aptly titled “Search &amp;#x26; Generate,” brought together the intersection of OpenSearch and Generative AI in a fantastic community gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Event: Search Meets Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t just another meetup - it was a historic moment as the &lt;strong&gt;first ever OpenSearch meetup in Israel&lt;/strong&gt;. The evening was perfectly described as “search meets story, index meets imagination,” and it truly lived up to that promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Talk: WTF Are Embeddings?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;strong&gt;“WTF Are Embeddings?”&lt;/strong&gt; - a friendly dive into the mathematical magic behind embeddings. The talk covered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What embeddings actually are&lt;/strong&gt; and why they matter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which embeddings to choose&lt;/strong&gt; for different use cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to generate them&lt;/strong&gt; effectively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical insights&lt;/strong&gt; from real-world implementations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal was to make embeddings accessible and fun, demystifying the concepts that power modern AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Introducing Shraga: A Minimal RAG Framework for Production]]></title><description><![CDATA[I published an article about Shraga, an open-source RAG framework I created with Big Data Boutique - designed to build production-ready GenAI applications without the bloat.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/shraga-rag-framework/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/shraga-rag-framework/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share that I’ve published an article on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/building-rag-apps-without-the-bloat-meet-shraga-c6cb31&quot;&gt;Big Data Boutique blog&lt;/a&gt; introducing &lt;strong&gt;Shraga&lt;/strong&gt;, an open-source RAG framework that I created together with the team at Big Data Boutique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problem We Solved&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article, titled &lt;strong&gt;“Building RAG Apps Without the Bloat: Meet Shraga”&lt;/strong&gt;, addresses a common challenge we’ve encountered across multiple client projects: existing RAG frameworks often abstract too much, come with heavy dependencies, and become obstacles when you need to understand what’s happening under the hood or ship something reliable to production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shraga was born from our real-world experience building RAG systems across different industries and use cases. We needed something that could serve us in both prototyping and production environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What Makes Shraga Different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shraga is designed around key principles that emerged from our production experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimal dependencies&lt;/strong&gt; - Start quickly without heavyweight abstractions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flow-based architecture&lt;/strong&gt; - Modular, composable units that are easy to test and debug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiple provider support&lt;/strong&gt; - Works with different LLM providers, embedders, and retrievers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built-in production features&lt;/strong&gt; - Authentication, logging, analytics, and cost tracking from day one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive complexity&lt;/strong&gt; - Start simple and evolve to clean, modular, well-typed code as projects mature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Core Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The framework centers around &lt;strong&gt;Flows&lt;/strong&gt; - modular units of logic that receive input, perform actions (which may or may not involve an LLM), and return responses. This design treats everything consistently: answering questions, fetching data, or chaining other flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article includes detailed code examples showing how to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build custom flows that integrate with any service (AWS Knowledge Bases, Pinecone, OpenSearch, Elasticsearch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the FastAPI layer for production concerns (auth, logging, performance tracking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handle ingestion and embedding with pluggable components&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy with the included React UI or use the API headlessly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From Prototype to Production&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aspect I’m particularly proud of is how Shraga supports the complete RAG application lifecycle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POC/Prototyping&lt;/strong&gt; - Start with Jupyter notebooks or simple Python scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal testing&lt;/strong&gt; - Use the built-in UI for design partner feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Production deployment&lt;/strong&gt; - Leverage security, analytics, and cost optimization features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iteration and improvement&lt;/strong&gt; - Built-in tools for evaluation and user feedback collection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Open Source and Available Now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shraga is completely open source and available on GitHub:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main framework&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ShragaAI/shraga&quot;&gt;github.com/ShragaAI/shraga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UI components&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ShragaAI/shraga-ui&quot;&gt;github.com/ShragaAI/shraga-ui&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working tutorial&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ShragaAI/shraga-tutorial&quot;&gt;github.com/ShragaAI/shraga-tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why We Built This&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s been working with search technologies for years and now focuses heavily on GenAI applications, I’ve seen firsthand how the gap between demo and production can derail projects. Shraga represents our opinionated take on what a production-ready RAG framework should look like - minimal enough to understand, powerful enough to scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Full Article&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dive into the complete framework overview and implementation details: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/building-rag-apps-without-the-bloat-meet-shraga-c6cb31&quot;&gt;Building RAG Apps Without the Bloat: Meet Shraga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article includes detailed architecture explanations, code examples, and practical guidance for getting started. Whether you’re evaluating RAG frameworks or looking for alternatives to heavier solutions, Shraga offers a fresh perspective on building GenAI applications that can actually make it to production.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Tutorial: Building Vector Search Applications with OpenSearch]]></title><description><![CDATA[I published a comprehensive hands-on tutorial on the Big Data Boutique blog demonstrating how to use OpenSearch as a vector database with real-world recipe data.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/opensearch-vector-database-tutorial/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/opensearch-vector-database-tutorial/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share my latest tutorial on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/recipes-to-vectors-using-opensearch-as-vector-database-aba607&quot;&gt;Big Data Boutique blog&lt;/a&gt;, where I dive deep into using OpenSearch as a vector database through a practical, hands-on approach with real recipe data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Tutorial Covers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article, titled &lt;strong&gt;“Recipes to Vectors: Using OpenSearch as Vector Database”&lt;/strong&gt;, takes you through the complete journey of building a vector-powered search application. Using a Kaggle recipe dataset, we explore how to transform text into searchable vectors and implement different search strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tutorial covers the entire workflow from data to deployment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dataset selection and preparation&lt;/strong&gt; - Working with real recipe data including ingredients, instructions, and metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embedding model selection&lt;/strong&gt; - Choosing and implementing Cohere’s embed-english-v3 model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Index configuration&lt;/strong&gt; - Setting up OpenSearch with proper k-NN settings and vector field mappings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embedding construction&lt;/strong&gt; - Combining multiple fields into meaningful text representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data ingestion&lt;/strong&gt; - Using OpenSearch’s Bulk API to index vectors efficiently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search implementation&lt;/strong&gt; - Building keyword search, semantic search, and hybrid search queries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Practical, Code-First Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this tutorial unique is its hands-on nature. Rather than just explaining concepts, we work with actual data and provide complete code examples available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BigDataBoutique/opensearch-semantic-search-tutorial&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. You’ll see how to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transform recipe names, ingredients, and instructions into effective embedding text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure OpenSearch indices with proper k-NN plugin settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handle real-world search scenarios like finding “Asian-inspired chicken recipes with noodles and peanuts”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement hybrid search to combine semantic understanding with structured filtering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building on the Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial represents the second article in our vector search implementation series. It builds on the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/vector-search-introduction/&quot;&gt;foundational concepts&lt;/a&gt; we covered earlier while complementing the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/semantic-search-elasticsearch-tutorial/&quot;&gt;Elasticsearch-focused tutorial&lt;/a&gt; I shared previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of working with recipe data is that it demonstrates both structured (categories, cooking time) and unstructured (instructions, ingredients) data scenarios - making it an excellent example for understanding when to use keyword search versus semantic search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why This Matters for Developers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s been working extensively with search technologies and now focuses on GenAI applications, I believe that understanding the low-level mechanics of vector databases is crucial. This tutorial gives you the foundation to build more sophisticated applications like recommendation engines, RAG systems, and AI-powered search experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Complete Tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dive into the full hands-on guide on the Big Data Boutique blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/recipes-to-vectors-using-opensearch-as-vector-database-aba607&quot;&gt;Recipes to Vectors: Using OpenSearch as Vector Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re new to vector search or looking to understand OpenSearch’s specific implementation, this tutorial provides the practical knowledge you need to start building vector-powered applications today.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Tutorial: Building Semantic Search Applications with Elasticsearch]]></title><description><![CDATA[I published a comprehensive hands-on tutorial on the Big Data Boutique blog about building hybrid search applications using Elasticsearch as a vector database.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/semantic-search-elasticsearch-tutorial/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/semantic-search-elasticsearch-tutorial/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share that I’ve published a new comprehensive tutorial on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/semantic-search-application-with-elasticsearch-vector-database-ceed7f&quot;&gt;Big Data Boutique blog&lt;/a&gt; about building semantic search applications with Elasticsearch as a vector database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Tutorial Covers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article, titled &lt;strong&gt;“Semantic Search Application with Elasticsearch Vector Database”&lt;/strong&gt;, provides a hands-on approach to building hybrid search applications that combine both keyword and semantic search capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on concepts from our previous introduction to vector search, this tutorial dives deep into the practical implementation details. We work directly with Elasticsearch’s low-level APIs to handle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector mapping and configuration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embedding generation and indexing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hybrid search query construction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance optimization techniques&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s been working extensively with search technologies and now specializing in GenAI applications, I believe that understanding how to properly implement semantic search is crucial for modern applications. The combination of traditional keyword search with semantic understanding creates powerful search experiences that can better understand user intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Hands-On Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than just covering theory, this tutorial takes you through building a real application. You’ll learn how to leverage Elasticsearch as a vector database while gaining a deeper understanding of how vector-powered applications work under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Full Tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the complete tutorial on the Big Data Boutique blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/semantic-search-application-with-elasticsearch-vector-database-ceed7f&quot;&gt;Semantic Search Application with Elasticsearch Vector Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re new to vector search or looking to deepen your understanding of Elasticsearch’s vector capabilities, this tutorial provides practical insights you can apply to your own projects.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Article: Understanding Vector Search in OpenSearch and Elasticsearch]]></title><description><![CDATA[I published a foundational article on the Big Data Boutique blog introducing vector search concepts and how they work in OpenSearch and Elasticsearch.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/vector-search-introduction/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/vector-search-introduction/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to share that I’ve published a comprehensive introduction to vector search on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/opensearch-and-elasticsearch-vector-search-an-introduction-6af584&quot;&gt;Big Data Boutique blog&lt;/a&gt;, exploring how this powerful search technology works in OpenSearch and Elasticsearch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Article Covers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article, titled &lt;strong&gt;“OpenSearch and Elasticsearch Vector Search: An Introduction”&lt;/strong&gt;, provides a foundational understanding of vector search technology and its implementation in modern search engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece explores the evolution from traditional keyword-based search to semantic search powered by dense vector embeddings. I break down complex concepts into digestible explanations, covering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The fundamentals of vector search&lt;/strong&gt; and how it differs from keyword search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyword search under the hood&lt;/strong&gt; - understanding BM25 and Bag of Words representation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embeddings and dense vectors&lt;/strong&gt; - how AI models transform text into meaningful numerical representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;k-NN vs ANN algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; - the trade-offs between accuracy and performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical use cases&lt;/strong&gt; including semantic search, recommendation engines, and multimedia search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bridging Theory and Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who’s spent years working with Elasticsearch and now focuses on GenAI applications, I wanted to create content that bridges the gap between traditional search and modern AI-powered approaches. The article shows how vector search addresses the limitations of keyword search - from handling synonyms to capturing semantic context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why This Foundation Matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding vector search fundamentals is crucial for anyone working with modern search applications. Whether you’re building recommendation systems, implementing semantic search, or working with RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) applications, these concepts form the backbone of how search engines can understand meaning rather than just matching keywords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Full Article&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dive into the complete introduction on the Big Data Boutique blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigdataboutique.com/blog/opensearch-and-elasticsearch-vector-search-an-introduction-6af584&quot;&gt;OpenSearch and Elasticsearch Vector Search: An Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article sets the foundation for more advanced topics we’ll be covering, including the hands-on tutorial for building semantic search applications that I shared in my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/semantic-search-elasticsearch-tutorial/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Certification: AWS Certified AI Practitioner]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’m excited to share that I’ve earned the AWS Certified AI Practitioner certification! AWS Certified AI Practitioner validates in-demand…]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-ai-practitioner-certification/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/aws-ai-practitioner-certification/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share that I’ve earned the &lt;strong&gt;AWS Certified AI Practitioner&lt;/strong&gt; certification!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Certified AI Practitioner validates in-demand knowledge of artificial intelligence (AI), machine learning (ML), and generative AI concepts and use cases. Sharpen your competitive edge and position yourself for career growth and higher earnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This certification demonstrates my commitment to staying at the forefront of AI and ML technologies. You can learn more about this certification on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/certification/certified-ai-practitioner/&quot;&gt;official AWS page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Article: Building Blazing Fast Reports with Elastic Transforms and ES|QL]]></title><description><![CDATA[I published an article on Medium demonstrating how to create high-performance reporting infrastructure using Elasticsearch Transforms and the new ES|QL query language.]]></description><link>https://lizozom.com/blog/elastic-transforms-esql-reporting/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lizozom.com/blog/elastic-transforms-esql-reporting/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share that I’ve published a practical article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@lizka.k/create-blazing-fast-reports-with-elastic-transforms-and-es-ql-ef918e7b384f&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; demonstrating how to solve reporting performance challenges using Elasticsearch Transforms combined with the newly announced ES|QL (Elasticsearch Query Language) from ELK 8.14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Challenge: Slow and Cumbersome Reporting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article addresses a real-world problem I encountered while working with a client whose reporting system was struggling with performance issues as data volumes increased. Generating reports had become a bottleneck, preventing timely business decisions and creating maintenance headaches for the development team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Solution: Elastic Transforms + ES|QL&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I demonstrate how combining these two powerful Elasticsearch features can dramatically improve reporting performance while making queries more intuitive and maintainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why Traditional Approaches Fall Short&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article explores why directly querying large indices with KQL (Kibana Query Language) creates problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex and hard-to-maintain queries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nested JSON responses&lt;/strong&gt; requiring additional server-side processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance degradation&lt;/strong&gt; as data moves to cold storage or indices grow large&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Better Approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I show how to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define transforms&lt;/strong&gt; that continuously aggregate data from source indices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create optimized reporting indices&lt;/strong&gt; with pre-calculated metrics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use ES|QL&lt;/strong&gt; to query transformed data with SQL-like syntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the Complete Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the full article with detailed implementation steps: &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@lizka.k/create-blazing-fast-reports-with-elastic-transforms-and-es-ql-ef918e7b384f&quot;&gt;Create BLAZING fast reports with Elastic Transforms and ES|QL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article represents the practical application of advanced Elasticsearch features to solve real business problems - something I’m passionate about as both a former Elastic team member and current consultant helping organizations optimize their search and analytics infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>